<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fore-runner of revenge being two petitions, the one to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty, the other to the most Honourables [sic] Houses of Parliament : wherein is expressed divers actions of the late Earle of Buckingham, especially concerning the death of King James and the Marquesse Hamelton, supposed by poyson : also may be observed the inconveniences befalling a state where the noble disposition of the prince is mis-led by a favourite / by George Eglisham ...</title>
            <author>Eglisham, George, fl. 1612-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A83691</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E256</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206483</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12275100</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12275100</idno>
            <idno type="VID">132723</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A83691)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132723)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 142:7; 247:E119, no 15; 2496:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fore-runner of revenge being two petitions, the one to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty, the other to the most Honourables [sic] Houses of Parliament : wherein is expressed divers actions of the late Earle of Buckingham, especially concerning the death of King James and the Marquesse Hamelton, supposed by poyson : also may be observed the inconveniences befalling a state where the noble disposition of the prince is mis-led by a favourite / by George Eglisham ...</title>
                  <author>Eglisham, George, fl. 1612-1642.</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Eglisham ... published in 1626 'Prodromus vindictae' ... A German translation appeared the same year, but the earliest English edition known of the 'Forerunner of revenge' bears date 1642, though a letter of the period ... mentions the work as an English publication, 20 May 1626"--DNB, v. 6, p. 584-585.</note>
                  <note>Numerous erros in pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in: Thomason Collection, British Library; Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Buckingham, George Villiers, --  Duke of, 1592-1628.</term>
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625.</term>
               <term>Hamilton, James Hamilton, --  Marquis of, 1589-1625.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:132723:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Fore-Runner OF REVENGE. Being two Petitions: THE ONE To the KINGS moſt Excellent Majeſty. THE OTHER, To the moſt Honourable Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Wherein is expreſſed divers actions of the late Earle of <hi>Buckingham;</hi> eſpecially concerning the death of King <hi>Iames,</hi> and the Marqueſſe <hi>Hamelton,</hi> ſuppoſed by poyſon.</p>
            <p>Alſo may be obſerved the inconveniences befalling a State where the Noble diſpoſition of the Prince is miſ-led by a Favourite.</p>
            <p>By <hi>George Egliſham</hi> Doctor of Phyſick, and one of the Pyſicians to King <hi>Iames</hi> of happy memory, for his Majeſties perſon above ten yeers ſpace.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> in the yeer, 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:132723:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Potent Monarch CHARLES King of great Britaine.</head>
            <head type="sub">The humble Petition of <hi>George Egliſham,</hi> Doctor of Phyſick, lately one of King <hi>IAMES</hi> his Phyſicians for his Majeſties perſon, above the ſpace of ten yeeres.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O better motive there is for a ſafe government then the ſafe meditation of death, (equalling Kings with Beggars) and the exact juſtice of God requiring of them, that the good ſuffring inmiſery this life, ſhould receive joy in the other; and the wicked flouriſhing ſecurely in this, might be puniſhed in the other. That which pleaſeth, laſteth but a moment; which tormenteth, is everlaſting. Many things we ſee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewarded or unpuniſhed in this inferiour World, which in the univerſall weight of Gods juſtice, muſt be counterpoiſed elſwhere. But wilfull and ſecret murther hath ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom been obſerved to undiſcovered or unpuniſhed even in this life, ſuch a particular and notable revenge perpetually followeth it, to the end that they who are either A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts or Matchiaveliſts, may not truſt too much to their wits in doing ſo horrible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice. Would to God your Majeſty would well conſider what I have often ſaid to my Maſter, King <hi>Iames,</hi> the greateſt policy is honeſty; and howſoever any man ſeeme to himſelf wiſe in compaſſing his deſires by tricks, yet in the end he will prove a foole: for falſhood ever deceiveth her own maſter at length, as the Devill (author of all fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood) always doth, leaving his adherents deſolate, when they have the greateſt need of his help; No falſhood without injuſtice, no injuſtice without falſhood, albeit it were in the perſon of a King.</p>
            <p>There is no Judge in the World more tied to do juſtice then a King, whoſe corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion tyeth him unto it by ſolemne oath, which if he violate, he is falſe and perjured.</p>
            <p>It is juſtice that maketh Kings, juſtice that mayntains Kings, and injuſtice that brings Kings and Kingdomes to deſtruction to fall into miſery, to die like Aſſes in dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or a more beaſtly death, eternall infamy after death, as all Hiſtories from time to time do cleerly manifeſt.</p>
            <p>What need hath mankind of Kings but for juſtice? Men are not born for them, but they for men: what greater, what more royall occaſion in the World could be offered to your Ma. to ſhew your impartiall diſpoſition in matters of juſtice at the firſt entry of your
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:132723:2"/>Reign, then this which I offer in my juſt complaint againſt <hi>Buckingham,</hi> by whom your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſuffereth your ſelf ſo far to be led, that your beſt ſubjects are in doubt whether he is your King, or you his. If your Majeſty know and conſider how he hath tyrannized over his Lord and Maſter King <hi>Iames,</hi> (the worldly Creatour of his fortunes) how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent, how ingrate an Oppreſſor, what a murtherer and traytor he hath proved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf towards him, how treacherous to his upholding friends the Marqueſs of <hi>Hamelton,</hi> and others, your Majeſty may think (giving way to the Laws demanded againſt him) to yield a moſt glorious field for your Majeſty to walk in, and diſplay the banner of your Royall vertues.</p>
            <p>Your Majeſty may perhaps demand, what intereſt I have therein, what have I to doe therewith, that I ſhould ſtir, all others being quiet? Sir, the quietneſſe or ſtirring of others, expecteth only a beginning from mee, whom they know ſo much obliged to ſtirre, as none can be more, both in reſpect of knowledge of paſſages, and in regard of humane obligation, and of my independancy from the accuſed, or any other that his power or credit can reach unto, many know not what I know therein, others are little or nothing beholding to the dead; others albeit they know it as well as I, and are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged as deep as I, yet dare not complain ſo ſafely as I, being out of their reach, who are inſeparable from him by his inchantments, and all to obſcure my ſelfe, untill the power of juſt revenge upon him be obtained from God.</p>
            <p>What I know ſufficient againſt him, I have ſet downe in my petition againſt him to the Parliament; to which if your Majeſty diſmiſſe him, ſequeſtred from your Majeſty chiefly in an accuſation of treaſon, you ſhall doe what is juſt, and deliver your ſelf and your Kingdome from the captivity in which hee holdeth them, and your Majeſty op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. How eaſily I may eclipſe my ſelfe from his power to do mee harme, unleſſe hee hath legions of infernall ſpirits at his command to purſue mee, your Majeſty may well know, I being <hi>ultra mare,</hi> to theſe Dominions where he ruleth and rageth.</p>
            <p>How far I am obliged to complain more then others, I will in few words expreſſe, that neither your Majeſty nor any man may think otherwiſe but that I have moſt juſt reaſon not to be ſilent in a wrong ſo intolerable, the intereſt of bloud which I have to any of them, of whoſe death I complaine either by the Houſe of <hi>Balgony, Lunday</hi> or <hi>Silverton-Hill,</hi> albeit it is eaſie to be made manifeſt and ſufficient to move me, yet it is not the ſole motive of my breach of ſilence, but the intereſt of received courteſie, and the heap of infallible tokens of true affection, is more then ſuffient to ſtir me thereto, unleſſe I would prove the moſt ingrate in the World, and ſenſeleſſe of the greateſt inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that can be done unto my ſelf; for who killed King <hi>James</hi> and Marqueſſe <hi>Hamel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> in that part of the injury which is done unto me therein, hee hath done as much as robbed me of my life, and all my fortunes and friends.</p>
            <p>With ſuch conſtant and loving impreſſions of me as are neither to be recovered not duly valued: for his Majeſty from the third yeer of my age, did practiſe honorable to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of ſingular favour towards me, daily augmented them in word, in writ, in deed, accompanied them with gifts, patents, offices, recommendations both in private and publike, at home and abroad graced ſo far, that I could ſcarce aske any thing, but I could have obtained it.</p>
            <p>How much honour he hath done unto me there needs no witneſſe unto your Majeſty, who is ſufficient for many; no leſſe is my Lord Marqueſſe <hi>Hameltons</hi> friendſhip eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by mutuall obligation of moſt acceptable offices continued by our anceſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:132723:3"/>theſe three generations, ingraven in the tender minds and yeers of the Marqueſſe and me in the preſence of our Sovereigne King <hi>Iames.</hi> For when the Marqueſſe his Father, who with the right hand on his head and the left on mine, did offer us (young in yeers) ſo joyned, to kiſſe his Majeſties hand, recommending me to his Majeſties favour, ſaid, I take God to witneſſe, that this young mans father was the beſt friend that ever I had, or ſhall have in this World. Whereupon the young Lord reſolved to put truſt in mee, and I fully to addict my ſelf to him, to deſerve of him as much commendations as my father did of his father.</p>
            <p>This Royall celebration of our friends rooted it ſelf ſo deep in my minde, that to my ſelf I purpoſed this remembrance, giving it to my young Lord, and to my famillar friends, and ſet it upon the books of my ſtudy, <hi>Semper</hi> Hameltonium, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Always the King and <hi>Hamelton</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Within thy breaſt conſerve,</l>
               <l>What ever be thy actions,</l>
               <l>Let Princes two deſerve.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Neither was it in vain, for both our loves increaſed with our age, the Marqueſſe promiſing to engage his life and whole eſtate for me, if need were and ſo ſhare his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes with me; and not onely promiſing, but alſo performing when ever there was oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion: yea, for my ſake offering to hazard his life in combat, whoſe mind in wiſhing me well, whoſe tongue in honouring of me, and whoſe hands and means in defending me (both abſent and preſent unto the laſt period of his life) hath ever aſſiſted me.</p>
            <p>I ſhould be more tedious then were fit, if I ſhould rehearſe every particular favour ſo manifeſtly knowne to the whole Court, and to the friends of us both: who then can juſtly blame me, demanding juſtice as well for the ſlaughter of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melton,</hi> as of my moſt gracious Sovereigne King <hi>Iames,</hi> ſeeing I know whom to accuſe; My profeſſion of Phyſick, nor my education to letters, cannot ſerve to hinder me from undertaking the hardeſt enterprize that ever any <hi>Roman</hi> undertook, ſo far as the Law of conſcience will give way.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why ſhould I ſtay at the decay</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Hameltons</hi> the hope,</l>
                  <l>Why ſhall I ſee thy foe ſo free,</l>
                  <l>Vnto this joy give ſcope?</l>
                  <l>Rather I pray a dolefull day</l>
                  <l>Set me in cruell fate:</l>
                  <l>Then thy death ſtrange without revenge,</l>
                  <l>Or him in ſafe eſtate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This ſoule to heavens, hand to the dead I vow,</l>
                  <l>No fraudfull minde, nor trembling hand I have:</l>
                  <l>If pen it ſhun, the ſword revenge ſhall follow,</l>
                  <l>Soule, Pen and Sword, what thing but juſt doe crave.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>What affection I bore to the living, the ſame ſhall accompany the dead: for when (whoſe truth and ſincerity was well knowne unto me) told me that it was better
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:132723:3"/>that the chiefeſt of my friends the Marqueſſe of <hi>Hamelton,</hi> to be quiet at home in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> then eminent in Court of <hi>England;</hi> to whom by the opinion of the wiſer ſort, his being at Court will coſt him no leſſe then his life, ſith that I ſtretching forth mine arme (apprehending ſome plots laid againſt him) anſwered, if no man dare to revenge his death, I vow to God this hand of mine ſhall revenge it, ſcarcely any other cauſe to be found, then the bond of our cloſe friendſhip, why in the ſcrowle of Noble mens names who were to be killed, I ſhould be ſet down next to the Marqueſſe of <hi>Hamelton</hi> and under theſe words, viz. <hi>(the Marqueſſe and Doctor Egliſham to embalme him)</hi> to wit, to the end that no diſcoverer or revenger ſhould be left, this roll of names, I know not by what deſtiny, was found neere to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> about the time of the Duke of <hi>Richmond</hi> his death, and brought to the Lord Marqueſſe by his cozen the daughter of the Lord <hi>Oldbarre,</hi> one of the privy Councell of <hi>Scotland,</hi> did cauſe no terror in mee untill I did ſee the Marqueſſe poyſoned, and remembred that the reſt therein noted, were dead, and my ſelfe next pointed at only ſurviving: why ſtay I any more, the cauſe requireth no more the pen but the ſword?</p>
            <p>I doe not write ſo boldly, becauſe I am amongſt the Dukes enemies, but I have reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my ſelfe to his enemies, becauſe I was reſolved to write and doe earneſtly againſt him, as may very well appeare: for ſince the Marqueſſe of <hi>Hameltons</hi> death, the moſt noble Marqueſſe <hi>de Fiatta;</hi> Embaſſadour for the moſt Chriſtian King of <hi>France,</hi> and alſo Buckingham his mother ſent on every ſide to ſeeke me, inviting me to them, but I did forſake them, knowing certainly the falſhood of <hi>Buckingham</hi> would ſuffer the Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador rather to receive an affront then to be unſatisfied of his blood-thirſty deſire of my blood, to ſilence me with death, (for according to the proverb <hi>The dead cannot bite</hi>) if he could have found me: for my Lord <hi>Duke of Lenox,</hi> who was often croſſed by <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kingham,</hi> with his brother; and the Earle of <hi>Southampton</hi> now dead was one of the roll found of thoſe that were to be murthered, well aſſured me, that where <hi>Buckingham</hi> once miſliked, no apologie, no ſubmiſſion, no reconciliation could keepe him from doing miſchiefe.</p>
            <p>Neither doe I write this in this faſhion ſo freely for any entertainment here preſent, which I have not, nor for any future which I have no ground to looke for, ſeeing <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kingham</hi> hath ſo much miſlead your Majeſty, that he hath cauſed not only here, but alſo in all Nations, all <hi>Britaine</hi> Natives to be diſgraced and miſtruſted, your Majeſties moſt royall word, which ſhould be inviolable, your hand and ſeal which ſhould be uninfrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable, to be moſt ſhamefully violated, and your ſelfe to be moſt ingrate for your kind uſage in <hi>Spaine,</hi> which <hi>Buckingham</hi> maketh to be requited with injuries in a moſt baſe manner; under proteſtation of friendſhip, a bloody war being kindled on both ſides, whereby he hath buried with King <hi>Iames,</hi> the glorious name of <hi>Peace-making King,</hi> who had done much more juſtly and adviſedly if hee had procured peace unto Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, whereby ſmall hope I have of obtaining juſtice on my moſt juſt complaint, unto which my deare affection unto my deare friends murthered, and extream deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Buckingham</hi> his violent proceedings hath brought me. Your Ma: may finde moſt juſt cauſes to accuſe him in my Petition to the Parliament which ſhall ſerve for a touchſtone to your Majeſtie, and a whetſtone to me and many other Scotſmen; and which if it be neglected, will make your Majeſty to incurre a cenſure amongſt all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous men in the world, that your Majeſty will be loath to heare of, and I am aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to expreſſe at this time,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:132723:4"/>
               <q>A Serpent lurketh in the graſſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>No other way there is to be found to ſave your honour, but to give way to Juſtice againſt that traytor <hi>Buckingham,</hi> by whom manifeſt danger approacheth to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, no otherwiſe then death approached to King <hi>Iames.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If your Majeſty will therefore take any courſe therein, the examination upon oath of all thoſe that were about the King and the Marqueſſe of <hi>Hamelton</hi> in their ſickneſſe, or at their deaths, or after their deaths, before indifferent Judges (no dependants on <hi>Buckingham</hi>) will ſerve for ſufficient proofe of <hi>Buckingham</hi> his guiltineſſe. In the meane time, untill I ſee what will be the iſſue of my complaint, without any more ſpeech I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Majeſties daily Suppliant,</hi> George Egliſham.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To the moſt Honourable the Nobilitie, Knights and Burgeſſes of the Parliament of ENGLAND.</head>
            <head type="sub">The humble Petition of <hi>George Egliſham</hi> Doctor of Phyſicke, and one of the Phyſitians to K. <hi>James</hi> of happy memory, for his Majeſties perſon above the ſpace of ten yeares.</head>
            <p>WHereas the chiefe humane care of Kings, and Courts of Parliament, is the preſervation and protection of the ſubjects lives, liberties and eſtates, from private and publicke injuries, to the end that all things may be carried in the equall ballance of Juſtice, without which no monarchy, no Common-wealth no ſociety, no family, yea no mans life or eſtate can conſiſt, albeit never ſo little: It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be thought unjuſt to demand of Kings and Parliaments the cenſure of wrongs, the conſideration whereof was ſo great in our Monarch of happy memory King JAMES, that he hath often publickly proteſted, even in the preſence of his appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant heire, that if his owne ſonne ſhould commit murther, or any ſuch execrable act of injury, he would not ſpare him, but would have him dye for it, and would have him more ſeverely puniſhed then any other: For he very well obſerved, no greater injuſtice, no injury more intollerable can be done by man to man, then murther. In all other wrongs fortune hath recourſe, the loſſe of honour or goods may be repaired, ſatisfaction may be made, reconciliation may be procured, ſo long as the party inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red is alive. But when the party murthered is bereft of his life, what can reſtore it? what ſatisfaction can be given him? where ſhall the murtherer meet with him to be reconciled to him, unleſſe he be ſent out of this world to follow the ſpirit, which by his wickedneſſe he hath ſeparated from his body? Therefore of all injuries, of all the acts of injuſtice, of all things moſt to be looked into, murther is the greateſt: And of all murthers, the poyſoning under truſt and profeſſion of friendſhip, is the moſt hey,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:132723:4"/>nous. which if you ſuffer to goe unpuniſhed, let no man thinke himſelfe ſo ſecure to live amongſt you, as amongſt the wildeſt and moſt furious beaſts in the world: for by vigilancy and induſtry means may be had to reſiſt of evict the moſt violent beaſt that ever nature bred, but from falſe and treacherous hearts, from poyſoning murthers, what wit of wiſedome can defend?</p>
            <p>This concerneth your Lordſhips every one in particular, as well as my ſelfe. They (of whoſe poyſoning your Petitioner complaineth) <hi>viz.</hi> King JAMES, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of HAMELTON, and others whoſe names after ſhall bee expreſſed, have been the moſt eminent in the Kingdome and ſate on theſe Benches whereon your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours doe now ſit. The party whom your Petitioner accuſeth is the Duke of Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, woo is ſo powerfull, that unleſſe the whole body of a Parliament lay hold on him, no juſtice can be had of him: For what place is there of Juſtice, what office of the Crowne, what degree of honour in the Kingdome, which he hath not ſold? And ſold in ſuch craft that he can ſhake the buyer out of them, and intrude others at his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>All the Judges of the Kingdome, all the Officers of State, are his bound vaſſals, or allies are afraid to become his out-caſts, as it is notorious to all his Majeſties true and loving ſubjects; yea, ſo farre hath his ambitious practice gone, that what the King would have done, could not be done if hee oppoſed it, whereof many inſtances may be given, whenſoever they ſhall be required: Neither are they unknown to this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable aſſembly, howſoever the means he uſeth be, whether lawfull or unlawfull, whether humane or diabolique, ſo he tortureth the Kingdome, that hee procureth the calling, breaking, or continuing of the Parliament, at his pleaſure, placing and diſpla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Officers of Juſtice, of the Councell of the Kings Court, of the Courts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, to his violent pleaſure, and as his ambitious villany moveth him: What hope then can your Petitioner have, that his complaint ſhould be heard; or being heard, ſhould take effect? To obtaine juſtice he may deſpaire; to provoke the Duke to ſend forth a poyſoner or murthere to diſpatch him, and ſend him after his dead friends al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready murthered, he may be ſure this to be the event. Let the event be what it will, come whatſoever can come, the loſſe of his owne life your Petitioner valueth not, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuffered the loſſe of the lives of ſuch eminent friends, eſteeming his life cannot be better beſtowed, then upon diſcovery of ſo heynous murthers, yea the juſtneſſe of the cauſe, the dearneſſe and neerneſſe of his friends murthered, ſhall prevaile ſo farre with him, that he ſhall unfold unto your Honours, and unto the whole world, againſt the accuſed, and name him the author of ſo great murthers, <hi>George Villers, Duke of Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kingham,</hi> which againſt any private man, are ſufficient for his apprehenſion and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And to make his complaint not very tedious, he will only for the preſent, declare unto your Honours, the two eminent murthers committed by <hi>Buckingham,</hi> to wit of the Kings Majeſty, and of the Lord Marqueſſe <hi>Hamelton,</hi> which for all the ſubtility of his poyſoning Art could not be ſo cunningly conveyed as the murtherer thought, but that God hath diſcovered manifeſtly the authour. And to obſerve the order of the time of their death, becauſe the Lord Marqueſſe <hi>Hamelton</hi> died firſt, his death ſhall be firſt related, even from the root of his firſt quarrell with <hi>Buckingham,</hi> albeit many other jarres have proceeded from time to time betwixt them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:132723:5"/>
            <head>Concerning the poyſoning of the Lord Marqueſſe HAMELTON.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>BVCKINGHAM</hi> once raiſed from the bottome of Fortunes wheele to the top, by what deſert, by what right or wrong, no matter it is, (by his carriage the proverb is verified) <hi>Nothing more proud then baſeſt blood, when it doth riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft.</hi> He ſuffered his ambition to carry himſelfe ſo farre, as to aſpire to match his blood with the Blood-Royall both of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> And well knowing, that the Marqueſſe of <hi>Hamelton</hi> was acknowledged by King <hi>Iames</hi> to be the prime man in his Dominions, who next to his owne line, in his proper ſeaſon might claime an heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Title to his Crowne of <hi>Scotland,</hi> by the Daughter of King <hi>Iames</hi> the ſecond, and to the Crown of <hi>England</hi> by <hi>Ioane</hi> of <hi>Sommerſet,</hi> wife to King <hi>Iames</hi> the firſt, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by an Act of Parliament Heretrix of <hi>Englond</hi> to be in her due ranke, never ſuffered the King to be at reſt, but urged him alwayes to ſend ſome of his Privie Councell to ſolicite the Marqueſſe to match his eldeſt ſonne with <hi>Buckinghams</hi> Neece, making great promiſes of conditions, which the meane family of the Bride could not performe, without the Kings liberality, to wit, fifty thouſand pound Sterling, valuing five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand Florens with the Earldome of Orkney, under the title of Duke, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Marqueſſe would accept, even to the firſt Duke of Britaine.</p>
            <p>The glorious Title of a Duke the Marqueſſe refuſed twice, upon ſpeciall reaſons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>The matter of money was no motive to cauſe the Marqueſſe to match his ſonne ſo unequall to his degree, ſeeing <hi>Buckingham</hi> himſelfe, the chiefe of her kindred was but a novice in Nobility, his father obſcure amongſt Gentlemen, his mother a Serving-wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: and he being infamous for his frequent conſultation with the Ring-leader of Witches, principally that falſe Doctor <hi>Lamb,</hi> publickly condemned for witch-craft<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereby the Marqueſſe knowing that the King was ſo farre bewitched to <hi>Buckingham</hi> thrt if he refuſed the match demanded, he ſhould find the kings deadly hatred againſ him; And ſeeing that <hi>Buckinghams</hi> Niece was not yet Nubile in yeares, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the marriage ſhould be conſirmed, a way might be found out to annull it, unto which he was forced by deceitfull importunity: therefore he yeelded unto the King deſire of the match; whereupon <hi>Buckingham</hi> and his faction fearing that delayes would bring lets, urged my Lord Marqueſſe to ſend for his ſonne upon a Sunday morning be times in all haſte from <hi>London</hi> to Court at <hi>Greenwich,</hi> where never a word was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of marriage to the young Lord, till a little before Supper, and the marriage mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> before the King after Supper, And to make it more authenticke, <hi>Buckingham</hi> cauſe his Neece to be lard in bed with the Marqueſſe his ſonne, for a ſhort time in the King Chamber, and in his Majeſties preſence, albeit the Bride was yet innubile. Many wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aſtoniſht at the ſudden newes thereof; all the Marqueſſe his friends fretting thereat an ſome writing unto him very ſcornfull letters for the ſame.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſſe having ſatisfied the Kings demands, did what hee could to preve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the confirmation of the marriage, and intended to ſend his ſonne beyond the ſeas travell through <hi>France,</hi> and ſo to paſſe his time a broad, untill that meanes were fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to unty that knot which <hi>Buckingham</hi> had urged the King to tie upon his ſonne.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:132723:5"/>
            <p>But Bucking ham to countermand the Marqueſſe his deſigne, cauſes the King and Prince to make the Marqueſſe his ſonne to be ſworne Gent: to the Princes Bed-chamber, and ſo to be detained with him within the Kingdome, untill that the Bride was at yeares ripe for marriage.</p>
            <p>The time expired that Buckinghams neece became marriageable, Buckingham ſent to the Marques to deſire him to make the mariage, to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pleatly confirmed.</p>
            <p>The marqueſſe (not willing to heare of any ſuch matter) anſwered briefely he ſcorned the motion.</p>
            <p>This anſwer reported to Buckingham, and ſeeing himſelfe like to be fruſt ated of his ambitious matching of his neece, and perceiving that the Lord Marqueſſe was able to raiſe a great faction againſt him, whether King <hi>Iames</hi> did live or die, was mightily incenſed againſt the Marqueſſe: At the firſt incounter with him, did challange him for ſpeaking diſdainfully of him and his houſe.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſſe replyed, he did not remember any offenſive words uttered by himſelfe againſt Buckingham. Buckingham then proudly ſaid unto him, out of the words of thy mouth I will judge thee: for you have ſaid, you ſcorne the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of matching with my houſe, which I made unto you. The marqueſſe anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that if he had ſaid ſo, it became not the Duke to ſpeake unto him in that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion. So Buckingham threatned to be revenged: The Marqueſſe uttered his defiance; and thus the quarrell began, which foure or five times was reiterated, and as often reconciled by Marqueſſe <hi>de Fietta,</hi> alittle before the Marqueſſe of Hamelton fell ſick, wherein it is very evident that the quarrel hath beene very violent, that needed ſo many reconciliations, The Dukes fire of his anger, being unextinguiſhable, as K. <hi>Iames</hi> did often cenſure him in his abſence, albeit that a favourite, that he was wonderfull vindicative, whoſe malice was inſatiable to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my Lo: Marqueſſe of Hamelton, did well ſhew it ſelfe as ſhall appeare hereafter.</p>
            <p>Hardly can any man tell whether by the Marqueſſe in his ſickneſſe, Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham was more ſuſpected then accuſed of the poyſon given or to be given him: for he would not taſte of any thing that was ſent him by any of Buckinghams friends; but he would have ſome of his ſervants taſte of it before: and for the love that was mutuall betweene him and your Petitioner (whom hee would never ſuffer to go out of his ſight during his ſickneſſe) your Petitioner caſt off all that he tooke in that time, unto whom his ſuſpition of Buckingham hee expreſſed by name before ſufficient witneſſe, who will teſtifie upon oath, if there bee any courſe taken therein for the ſearch thereof, all the time of his ſickneſſe he intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted your petitioner not to ſuffer my Lo: of Buckingham to come neere him, and your Petitioner having often ſent word, and alſo ſometimes fignified himſelfe to Buckingham, that there was no ſit opportunity to ſee the Marqueſſe, pretending ſomething to be miniſtred to him. But when your petitioner could finde no more excuſes, he told my Lo: Marques that he had put away my Lo: of Buckingham ſo often, that he could not keepe him away any longer, but that he muſt needes ſee him.</p>
            <p>Then he knowing Buckinghams viſitation to proceed of diſimulation, requeſted
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:132723:6"/>your petitioner at laſt to finde the means to get him away quiekly: which your Petitioner did, interrupting. Buckingham his diſcourſe, and intreating him to ſuffer my Lord Marqueſs to bee quiet.</p>
            <p>This did evidently ſhew my Lord Marqueſs his diſliking and diſtruſting of Buckingham, whereas hee was pleaſed with other Noblemens Company. All the time of his ſickneſſe, the Duke and my Lord Denbigh would not ſuffer his own ſon to come to him, pretending that he was alſo ſicke; which was falſe for the time that my Lord Marqueſs called for him. After this your Petitioner adviſed his Lordſhip to diſpoſe of his eſtate, and of his conſcience, his ſickneſſe was not without danger, which your Petitioner foure dayes before my Lords death, did in ſuch manner perceive, that hee had cauſe to commit all the care of his health to God and his Phyſitians, aſſuring howſoever hee had gotten wrong abroad, he ſhould get none in the cure of his diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>At length his Lordſhip burſt out in theſe words to my Lord Denbigh, It is a great cruelty in you, that you will not ſuffer my ſon to come to me when I am dying that I may ſee him, and ſpeake to him before I dye. So they delayed his comming with excuſes, untill my Lord his agony of death was neere, to the end that he ſhould not have time to give his ſon private inſtructions to ſhun the marriage of Buckinghams Neece, or to ſignifie unto him the fuſpition of poyſon: for they had rather his ſon ſhould know any thing, then either of theſe; yet many did ſuſpect his poyſon before he died: for two dayes before his death, two of his ſervants died with manifeſt ſigns and ſuſpition, of poyſon, the one belonging to the Wine-celler, the other to the Kitchin.</p>
            <p>The Fatall houre being come, that my Lord Marqueſs deceaſed, your Petitioner intreated all were preſent, to ſuffer no man to touch his body, untill that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to ſee it opened. For then he proteſted earneſtly, that all the time of his ſickneſſe, he judged it to be poyſon; but this poyſon was ſuch, and ſo farre gone, that none could help it: Nevertheles, to have the matter concealed, Buckingham would have him buried that ſame night in Weſtminſter Church, and the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of his buriall to be kept afterwards, ſaying, that ſuch delicate bodies as his could not be kept.</p>
            <p>But his friends taking hold of the cavet before given by your Petitioner, refuſed ſo to doe, and replied, that they would have him, as became him to bee buried in Scotland in his owne Chappell, where all his Anceſters have beene butied for more then theſe four hundred yeares; and that his body muſtbee viſited by his Phyſitians.</p>
            <p>No ſooner was he dead, when the force of the poyſou had overcome the force of his body, but it began to ſwell in ſuch ſort, that his Thighes were ſwolne ſixe times as bigge as their naturall proportion: his Belly became as the belly of an Oxe, his Arins as the natural quantity of Thighs, his Neck ſo broad as his Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, his Cheekes over the top of his Noſe, that his Noſe could not be ſeen or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, the skin of his fore-head two fingers high ſwolled, the haire of his beard, eye-browes and head, ſo farre diſtant one from another, as if an hundred had been taken oat bet weene each one; and when one did touch the haire, it came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:132723:6"/>with the skin as eaſily, as if one had pulled hay out of an heap of hay. He was all over his neck, breaſt, ſhoulders, armes, and browes I ſay of divers colours, full of waters of the ſame colour, ſome white, ſome blacke, ſome red, ſome yellow, ſome greene, ſome blew, and that as well within the body as without.</p>
            <p>Alſo the concavities of his Liver greene his ftomach in ſome places a little purpurated with a blew clammy water, adhering to the ſides of it. His Mouth and Noſe foaming blood mixt with froth mightily, of divers colours a yard high. Your Petitioner being ſent for to viſit his body, and his ſervants flocking about him, ſaying, See, ſee, preſently weeping, ſaid he was poyſoned, and that it was a thing not be ſuffered.</p>
            <p>Moreover, he ſaid, that albeit his ſpeech might coſt him his life, yet ſeeing his ſorrow had extorted that ſpeech out, he would make it manifeſt, and would have a Jury of Phyſitians. Preſently, ſome of my Lord Marqueſs of Hameltons friends ſaid, we muſt ſend to my Lord Duke, that he may ſend his Phyſitlans: but your Petitioner replied, what have we to doe with the Dukes Phyſitians? Let us have indifferent men. Captaine <hi>Hamelton</hi> hearing your Petitioner ſo boldly take ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions at Buckingham, and juding that he had good reaſon for what he had ſpoken, ſaid, for all that let us ſend to the Duke, and ſignifie, that they all who have ſeen the Marqueſs his body, both Phyſitians, Chyrurgeons, and others, may ſee that hee is poyſoned, and that his friends deſire more Phyſitians out of the Colledge of London, beſides the Dukes Phyſitians, to beare witneſſe in what caſe the Marqueſs his body is in; and then if the Dukes conſcience be guilty (ſaid the Captain,) it will ſhew it ſelf, as indeed it did: for the Duke being advertiſed hereof, ſent for his owne Phyſitians, and others out of London, whom he cauſed firſt to be brought unto him, before they went to ſee the Marqueſs his body, giving them his directions in theſe words, viz.</p>
            <p>
               <q>My Maſters, there is a bruit ſpread abroad, that the Marqueſſe of Hamelton is poyſoned; Goe ſee, but beware what you ſpeak of poyſon (which he ſaid in a hreatning forme of delivery) for every Noble man that dieth muſt be poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If his conſcience had not been guilty, ſhould not he have commanded the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itians to enquire by all meanes poſſible, and made it knowne rather then to uppreſſe the ſpeech of poyſoning ſo worthy a man.</p>
            <p>Theſe Phyſitians being come, your Petitioner with one hand leading Doctor <hi>More</hi> to the Table where the Marqueſs his body was layd, and with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her hand throwing off the cloth from the body ſaid to him, Look you here upon his ſpectacle.</p>
            <p>At the ſight whereof Doctor <hi>More</hi> lifting up both his hands, heart and eyes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Heavens, agoniſhed, ſaid, Jeſus bleſſe me, I never ſaw the like, I cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſtinguiſh a face upon him; and in like manner all the reſt of the Doctors, and ſo the Chirurgjons affirmed, that they never ſaw the like, albeit that they have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>availed and practiſed through the greateſt part of Eorope: onely one that ſaid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y Lo: of Southampton was bliſtered all within the breſt as my Lo: marqueſſes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:132723:7"/>was. Doctor <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> one of Buckinghams creature, ſeeing Doctor <hi>More</hi> &amp; others ſo amazed at the ſight of my Lords body, drew firſt him aſide, and then the others, one after another, and whiſpered them in the eare to ſilence them.</p>
            <p>Whereupon many went away without ſpeaking one word, the other who remained, acknowledged that thoſe accidents of the dead body, could not bee without poyſon; but they ſaid, they could not know how ſuch a ſubtile art of poyſoning could be brought into England; your Petitioner replyed that money would bring both the Art and the Artiſt from the furtheſt part of the World into England, from whence ſince your Petitioners departure, he hath conferred with the skilfulleſt Peſtmaſters that could be found, who viſite the bodies of thoſe that die of the venome of the peſt.</p>
            <p>They all admired the deſcription of my Lo: Marques his body, and teſtifie that never any of the peſt have ſuch accidents, but Carbuncles, Rubons, or Spots, no ſuch huge bliſters with waters, and ſuch a huge uniforme ſwelling to ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentions, above ſix times the naturall proportion. But he hath met with ſome who have practiſed the poyſoning of dogs, to try the forces of ſome Antidotes, and they have round that ſome poyſons have made the dogs ſick for a fortnight or more, without any ſwelling untill they were dead, and then they ſwelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove meaſure, and became bliſtered with waters of divers colours, and the haire came away with the skin when it was touched.</p>
            <p>The Phiſitians then who remained, were willing to certifie under their hands, that my Lo: Marqueſſe was poyſoned. But your petitioner told them it was not needefull, ſeeing we muſt needes attend Gods leaſure to diſcover the author, the manner being ſo apparant, and ſo many hundreds having ſeen the body to witneſſe it, for the doores were kept open for every man to behold and to bee witneſſe who would.</p>
            <p>The Duke of Buckingham making ſome counterfeit ſhew of ſorrow, two men of great quality, found no other ſhift to divert the ſuſpition of the poyſoning of the Marqueſſe from him, but to lay it upon his maſter the King, ſaying, that the marqueſſe for his perſon, ſpirit and carriage, was ſuch as he was born worthy to reigne; but the King his Maſter hated him to death, becauſe he had a ſpirit too much for the commonwealth; whereby the Duke did ſhew himſelfe no good ſubject to the King, who made the Kings honour to be tyranicall, and the King a blood-thirſty murtherer, and a moſt vile diſſembler, having heaped ſo many ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours daily upon the Marqueſſe even to the very laſt, making him Lord high Steward of his Majeſties houſe, and Judg of the very Court, whom he had made before Vice-roy of Scotland, for the time of the Parliament in Scotland, Earl of Cambridge, privie Councellor in England, and Knight of the Garter, as if hee had raiſed him to all theſe honours, that the murthering of him might be the leſſe ſuſpected to proceede from him.</p>
            <p>The Kings nature hath alwayes beene obſerved, to have beene ſo gracious and ſo free-hearted towards every one, that hee would never have wiſhed the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe any harme, unleſſe that Buckingham had put great jealouſies and fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s into as minde: for if any other had done it, he would have acquainted his favourite
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:132723:7"/>therewith. And then was it Buckinghams duty to remove from the King ſuch ſmiſtrous conceits of the Marqueſſe, as the marqueſſe hath often done of Buck<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ingham, upholding him upon all occaſions, and keeping the King from giving way to introduce any other favourite: wherefore Buckingham in that diverſion of the crime from him, hath not onely made the King but alſo himſelfe guilty of the Marqueſſes death</p>
            <p>But Buckinghams falſehood and ill intention, was long before rightly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, when he did what he could to make the E. of <hi>Netherſdale</hi> and my Lord <hi>Gordan</hi> (both neere kinſmen of my Lord Marqueſſe) ſo incenſed at him, that they had like all three to have killed one another, if it had not been that my Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe by his wiſdome, did let them all know, how they were abuſed.</p>
            <p>If any diſſimulation be greater then <hi>Buckingams,</hi> let any man judge: For when my Lord Marqueſſe his body was to bee tranſported from White-hall to his houſe at Biſhops-gate, <hi>Buckingham</hi> came out muffed and furred in his Coach giving out that he was ſicke for ſorrow of my Lord Marqueſſe his death; but as ſoone as he went to his houſe out of London, before his comming to the King, he triumphed and domineered with his faction ſo exceſſively, as if he had gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome great victory. And the next day comming to the King, put on a moſt lamentable and mournefull countenance for the death of the Marqueſſe. No grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter victory could he have gotten in his mind, then to have deſtroyed that man who would have fetched his head off his ſhoulders if he had out lived King <hi>Iames,</hi> to have knowne his carriage in the poyſoning of him in his ſickneſſe; wherefore he thought it neceſſary to remove the Marqueſſe beforehand.</p>
            <p>The ſame day that my Lord Marqueſſe died, <hi>Buckingham</hi> ſent my Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe his ſonne out of Towne, keeping him as priſoner, none could have pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate conference with him, untill his marriage of <hi>Buckinghams</hi> Neece was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat; but either my Lord of <hi>Denbigh</hi> or my lady of <hi>Denbigh,</hi> or my Lord Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> or the Counteſſe of <hi>Buckingham</hi> was preſent, that none could let him underſtand how his father was murthered. Even your petitioner himſelfe when he went to ſee him, was intreated not to ſpeake to him of the poyſoning of his father, which he did conceale at his firſt meeting, becauſe their ſorrow was too recent. But he was prevented of a ſecond meeting, neither would <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham</hi> ſuffer the young Lord to go to Scotland to ſee his Fathers Funerals, and to take order with his friends concerning his fathers eſtate, for feare that their intended marriage ſhould be overthrowne.</p>
            <p>This Captivity of the young Lord Marqueſſe laſted ſo long, untill that <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham</hi> cauſed his Majeſty, King CHARLS, to take the young Lord, with himſelfe and <hi>Buckingham,</hi> into St. <hi>Iames</hi> his Parke, diſcharging all others from following them; and there to perſwade and urge the young Lord, without any more delay to accompliſh the marriage with <hi>Buckingham</hi> his Neece, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly was performed: ſo that <hi>Buckingham</hi> truſteth and preſumeth, that albeit the young Lord ſhould underſtand how his father was poyſoned by his meanes, yet being married to his Neece, he would not ſtirre to revenge it, but comport with it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:132723:8"/>
            <p>To all that is obſerved before, it is wothy to be added, that the bruit went through <hi>London</hi> long before the Lord Duke of <hi>Richmonds</hi> death, or his brothers, or my Lord of <hi>Southamptons,</hi> or of the Marqueſs, that all the Noble men that were not of the Dukes faction, ſhould be poyſoned, and ſo removed out of his way.</p>
            <p>Alſo a Paper was found in Kings Street, about the time of the Duke of Richmonds death, wherein the Names of all thoſe Noblemen who have dyed ſince, were expreſſed; and your Petitioners Name alſo ſet next to my Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Hameltons</hi> Name, with theſe words <hi>(to embalme him)</hi> This Paper was brought by my Lord <hi>Oldbarrs</hi> Daughter, Couſin german to the Lord Marqueſs: Likewiſe a Mountebanke about that time, was greatly countenanced by the Duke of Buckingham, and by his means procured Letters Patents, and Recommendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the King, to practiſe his skill in Phyſick through all England: who comming to London, to ſell Poyſon, to kill man or beaſt within a yeare, or half a yeare, or two yeares, or a moneth or two, or what time prefixed any man deſired, in ſuch ſort that they could not be helped nor diſcovered. Moreover, the Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas before my Lord Marqueſs his death, one of the Prince his footmen ſaid, That ſome of the great ones at Court had gotten, Poyſon in theis belly, but he could not tell who it was.</p>
            <p>Here your Honours conſidering the premiſſes, of my Lord Duke of Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham his ambitious and moſt vindicative nature, his frequent quarrels with my Lord Marqueſſe, after ſo many reconciliations; his threatning of the Phyſitians, not to ſpeak of the poyſon; his triumphing after my Lord Marqueſſe his death; his detaining of his ſon almoſt priſoner, untill the Marriage was compleat with his Neece; the preceding bruit of poyſoning Buckingham his Adverſaries; the Paper of their Names found, with ſufficient intimation of their death, by the concluſion of the word <hi>(embalming)</hi> the Poyſon-monger, Mountebank, graced by <hi>Buckingham,</hi> may ſuffice for ground to take him and torture him, if he were a private man: And herein your Petitioner moſt earneſtly demandeth Juſtice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Traitor, ſeeing by Act of Parliament it is made Treaſon to conſpire the death of a Privie Councellor. Out of this Declaration, Interrogatories may be drawne for Examination of Witneſſes; wherein more is diſcovered to begin withall, then was laid open at the beginning of the Diſcoverie of the poyſoning of Sir <hi>Thomas Overbury.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:132723:8"/>
            <head>Concerning the poyſoning of King JAMES of happy memory, KING of GREAT BRITAINE.</head>
            <p>THe Duke of Buckingham being in Spaine, advertiſed by Letters, how that the King began to cenſure him in his abſence freely, and that many ſpake boldly to the King againſt him, and how the King had intelligence from Spaine of his unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy carryage in Spaine; and how the Marqueſſe <hi>Hamelton</hi> (upon the ſudden news of the Princes departure) had nobly reprehended the King for ſending the Prince with ſuch a young man, without experience, and in ſuch a private and ſudden man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, without acquainting the Nobility or Councell therewith, wrot a very kitter letter to the Marqueſſe of Hamelton, conceived new ambitious courſes of his owne, and uſed all the devices he could to diſguſt the Princes mind of the match with Spain, ſo far intended by the King, made haſte home; where, when he came, he ſo car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed himſelfe, that whatſoever the King commanded in his Bed-chamber, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolled in the next; yea, received Packets to the King from forraigne Princes, and diſpatched Anſwers without acquainting the King therewith, in a long time after. Whereat perceiving the King highly offended, and that the Kings mind was beginning to alter towards him, ſuffering him to be quarrelled and affronted in His Majeſties preſence; and obſerving that the King reſerved my Lord of Briſtol to be a rod for him, urging daily his diſpatch for France, and expecting the Earle of Gond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mor, who as it ſeemed was greatly eſteemed and wonderfully credited by the King, and would ſecond my Lord of Briſtol his accuſations againſt him. He knew alſo the King had vowed, that in ſpight of all the Devils in hell, he would bring the Spaniſh match a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout againe, and that the Marqueſſe of <hi>Inicoſa</hi> had given the King bad impreſſions of him, by whoſe articles of accuſation, the King himſelfe had examined ſome of the Nobility and Privie Councel, and found out in the examination, that <hi>Buckingham</hi> had ſaid after his comming from Spaine, that the King was now an old man, it was now time for him to be at reſt, and to be confined to ſome Parke, to paſſe the reſt of his time in hunting, and the Prince to be crowned.</p>
            <p>The more the King urged him to be gone to France, the more ſhifts he made to ſtay: for he did evidently ſee that the King was fully reſolved to rid himſelf of the oppreſſion wherein he held him.</p>
            <p>The King being ſick of a certaine Ague, and that in the Spring, was of it ſelfe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver found deadly; the Duke took his opportunity when all the Kings Doctors of Phyſick were at dinner, upon the Munday before the King dyed, without their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or conſent, offered to him a white powder to take: the which he a long time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed; but overcome with his flattering importunity, at length took it in wine, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately became worſe and worſe, falling into many ſwounings and paines, and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent fluxes of the belly, ſo tormented, that His Majeſty cryed out aloud of this white powder, Would to God I had never taken it, it will coſt me my life.</p>
            <p>In like manner alſo the Counteſſe of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> my Lord of <hi>Buckinghams</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:132723:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>mother, upon the Friday after, the Phyſitians alſo being abſent, and at Dinner, not made acquainted with her doings applyed a plaiſter to the Kings heart &amp; brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> whereupon he grew faint, ſhort breathed, and in a great Agony. Some of the Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans after dinner returning to ſee the King, by the offenſive ſmell of the plaiſter, perc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved ſomething to be about him hurtfull unto him and ſearched what it ſhould be, fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> it out, and exclaimed, that the King was poyſoned. Then <hi>Buckingham</hi> entring, com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manded the Phyſitians out of the room, cauſed one of them to be committed priſoner his own houſe, and another to be removed from Court, quarrelled with others of Kings ſervants in his ſick Majeſties own preſence, ſo far that he offered to draw ſword againſt them in his Majeſties ſight. And <hi>Buckinghams</hi> mother kneeling do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> before His Majeſty, cryed out with a brazen face, Iuſtice, Iuſtice; Sir, I demand-ſtice of your Majeſty. His Majeſty asked her for what? For that which their li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> are no wayes ſufficient to ſatisfie, for ſaying that my ſonne and I have poyſoned y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Majeſtie. Poyſoned me? ſaid he; with that turning himſelfe, ſwounded, and ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> removed.</p>
            <p>The Sunday after His Majeſtie dyed, and <hi>Buckingham</hi> deſired the Phyſitians <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> attended his Majeſtie, to ſigne with their hands a writ of teſtimonie, that the pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> which he gave him, was a good and ſafe medicine; which they refuſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Buckinghams</hi> creatures did ſpread abroad a rumor in London, that <hi>Buckingham</hi> was ſo ſrrry for his Majeſties death, that he would have dyed, that he would have led himſelfe if they had not hindred him; which your Petitioner purpoſely enqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> after of them that were neere him at that time, who ſaid, that neither in the tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> His Majeſties ſickneſſe, nor after his death, he was more moved, then if there happened either ſickneſſe or death to His Majeſtie.</p>
            <p>One day when his Majeſty was in great extremity, he rode poſt to <hi>London</hi> to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue his ſiſter in law to have her ſtand in ſackcloth in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> for adultery. And o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther time in his Majeſties Agonie, he was buſie in contriving and concluding a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage for one of his couſins.</p>
            <p>Immediately after his Majeſties death, the Phyſitian who was commanded to chamber, was ſet at liberty with a caveat to hold his peace; the others threatn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> they kept not good tongues in their heads.</p>
            <p>But in the mean time the Kings body and head ſwelled above meaſure, his h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> with the skin of his head ſtuck to the pillow, his nailes became looſe upon his fin and toes.</p>
            <p>Your Petitioner needeth to ſay no more to underſtanding men, only one thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeecheth, That taking the Traytor who ought to be taken without any feare of greatneſſe, the other waters may be examined, and the Acceſſaries with the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> puniſhed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:132723:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
